Preliminary Guide to John O. C. McCrillis Designs and Art Work
Yale University Arts Library
John O. C. McCrillis Designs and Art Work
1938-2003
AOB 18
Yale University Arts Library
2.5
(4 boxes and 1 flat file)
The collection consists of examples of graphic designs and art works created by John McCrillis, including painting and drawing, relief printing, lettering, and typography. Examples are drawn from his work at the Yale University Press as well as his freelance work and works produced at McCrillis's Penny-Whistle Press.
McCrillis, John O. C.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John O. C. McCrillis.
Conditions Governing Access
Curatorial permission required before use.
Biographical / Historical
John O. C. McCrillis studied at the Rhode Island School of Design in the 1930s and was one of the first students in the Graphic Design program at the Yale School of Art. After receiving an MFA from Yale in 1952, McCrillis took a position as a typographer with Yale University Press, where he worked until his retirement in 1979. He produced pamphlets, broadsides, keepsakes, greeting cards, and other works at his own Penny-Whistle Press and created works on a freelance basis for many institutions and organizations. In 1993, he published his autobiographical work, An Airman's Letters: and Other Recollections of World War II, May 18, 1942, to September 18, 1945, by the Penny-Whistle Press.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of examples of graphic designs and art works created by John McCrillis, including painting and drawing, relief printing, lettering, and typography. Examples are drawn from his work at the Yale University Press as well as his freelance work and works produced at McCrillis's Penny-Whistle Press.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Personal Files, 1947-2002. II. Early Work, 1940-1950. III. Non-Commissioned Work, 1938-2003. IV. Commissioned Work, 1940-1994.
Graphic arts; Drawings (visual works); Sketchbooks; Watercolors (paintings); Wood blocks (printing blocks); McCrillis, John O. C.; Penny-Whistle Press
- Personal Files, 1947-2002; Series I
  - Writings by and about McCrillis, 1970, 1975, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Announcements of McCrillis exhibitions and talks, 1947, 1971, 1999-2002 (Box 1)
  - Photographic negative, undated (Box 1)
- Early Work, 1940-1950; Series II
  Arrangement
  Material also housed in Oversize. See below for the Oversize listing.
  - Design, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Painting and drawing, undated (Box 1)
  - Relief printing, 1945, undated (Box 1)
  - Sketchbooks from drawing class with Josef Albers, 1950
    General note
    See Oversize Material, Box 4.
  - Wood blocks, undated (Box 3)
- Non-Commissioned Work, 1938-2003; Series III
  - Greeting cards
    - General, 1967, 1970-1988 (Box 1)
    - Holiday, 1938-1945, 1955-1974, 1984, 1991, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Proofs and color separation, 1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Lettering, 1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Painting and drawing, undated (Box 1)
  - Penny-Whistle Press
    - Broadsides and keepsakes, 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - Greeting cards, 1978, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Publications, 1978, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
      - Old Christmas proofs, 1978, undated (Box 1)
      - The Raven illustrations, undated (Box 1)
  - Photos of art works, 1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Printed books, 1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Wood blocks, undated (Box 3)
  - Works for friends, 1963-1971, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
- Commissioned Work, 1940-1994; Series IV
  The material in this series is arranged alphabetically by the name of client for whom the work was created. Works include greeting cards, pamphlets, brochures, logos, corporate identity, lettering, etc.
  - American Association for State and Local History, undated (Box 1)
  - American Association for the History of Medicine, 1967 (Box 1)
  - American Shakespeare Festival, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Association of American University Presses, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Branford Historical Society, 1976, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - The Children's Center, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Club of Odd Volumes, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Coggeshall Historical Association, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Colman/Parker, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation, 1988 (Box 1)
  - First Baptist Church, Branford, Connecticut, 1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Garden Club of New Haven, 1983, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Hallmark (not used), 1948, undated (Box 1)
  - The Hill-Stead Museum, 1966 (Box 1)
  - John W. Barden Apple Orchards, undated (Box 1)
  - The Johnsonians, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Marine Historical Association, undated (Box 1)
  - Mattatuck Historical Society, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Michael Boyle, Publisher, 1983 (Box 1)
  - New Haven Bicentennial Commission, circa 1976 (Box 1)
  - New Haven Colony Historical Society, 1975-1988, 1991 (Box 1)
  - New Haven Festival of Arts, 1972 (Box 1)
  - New Haven Police Department, 1961 (Box 1)
  - New Haven Symphony Orchestra, 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Old Sturbridge Village, 1965-1966, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Proprietors of New Haven City Burial Ground, undated (Box 1)
  - Redwood Library and Athenaeum, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Saint Thomas More Chapel, undated (Box 1)
  - Ticknor & Fields, 1980-1983, undated (Box 1)
  - Updike, undated (Box 1)
  - Walpole Society, undated (Box 1)
  - Woman's Seamen's Friend Society of Connecticut, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Yale University
    - A-Y, 1958-1972, 1984-1986, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Beinecke Library, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Elizabethan Club, undated (Box 1)
    - Silliman College, undated (Box 1)
    - Sterling Memorial Library, 1960-1962, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Yale University Art Gallery, 1971, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Yale University Press, 1954, 1963, 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous bookplates, 1968, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous letterheads/logos, undated (Box 1)
- Oversize Material
  - From Series II. Early Work
    - Design, painting and relief printing, 1949, undated (Box 2)
    - Sketchbooks from class with Josef Albers, 1950 (Box 4)
    - Wood blocks, undated (Box 3)
  - From Series III. Non-Commissioned Work
    - Greeting cards, 1963, undated (Box 2)
      See also Bsd 1.1.
    - Greeting cards, 1963, undated (Folder 1)
      See also Box 2.
    - Lettering, 1952-1989, undated (Box 2)
    - Painting and drawing, prints, and broadsides, 1975, 2000, undated (Box 2)
    - Painting and drawing, prints, and broadsides, 1975, 2000, undated (Folder 1)
    - Penny-Whistle Press material, 1976, 1993, undated (Box 2)
    - Printed works, 1974, undated (Box 2)
    - Wood blocks, undated (Box 3)
  - From Series IV. Commissioned Work
    - American Association for State and Local History, undated (Box 2)
    - Armstrong Rubber Company, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Association of American University Presses, 1991 (Box 2)
    - Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation, 1987 (Folder 1)
    - Garden Club of New Haven, [1983] (Box 2)
    - Houghton Mifflin, undated (Box 2)
    - Joan Kahn Books/Clarion Books, undated (Box 2)
    - New Haven Colony Historical Society, 1999 (Box 2)
    - New Haven Historic District Commission, undated (Folder 1)
    - New Haven Symphony Orchestra, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Old Sturbridge Village, undated (Box 2)
    - Old Sturbridge Village, undated (Folder 1)
    - Orchestra New England, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Pilgrim Press, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Radcliffe Publishing Procedures Course, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Rhode Island School of Design, 1939, 1990, 2001 (Box 2)
    - Rhode Island School of Design, 1939, 1990, 2001 (Folder 1)
    - Trinity College, Watkinson Library, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Yale School of Organization and Management, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Yale University Library, undated (Box 2)
    - Yale University Press, 1952-1974 (Box 2)
    - Yale University Press, 1952-1974 (Folder 1)